A Finding Aid to the Grigory Gluckmann papers, circa 1910-2003, bulk 1920-1973, in the Archives of American Art AAA.glucgrig
Archives of American Art
Grigory Gluckmann papers
bulk 1920-1973
circa 1910-2003
AAA.glucgrig
Archives of American Art
2.4 Linear feet
The papers of painter Grigory Gluckmann measure 2.4 linear feet and date from circa 1910-2003, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920-1973. The collection documents his career as a painter in Paris, France, and Los Angeles, California. Included are biographical materials, such as identification and immigration papers, awards, and exhibition lists; a few letters from friends, family, and art galleries; three notebooks; exhibition announcements, catalogs, and one poster; photographs of Gluckmann, his wife Anna, and artwork; drawings, prints, and other original artwork; and four scrapbooks containing news clippings and exhibition printed material.
Gluckmann, Grigory, 1898-1973
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2012 by Richard B. Glickman, Grigory Gluckmann's nephew.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1920-2003 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Letters, 1941-1973 (1 Folder; Box 1)
Series 3: Notebooks, 1930-1971 (3 Folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1944-1977 (4 Folders; Box 1, OV 4)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1910-1973 (1 linear foot; Box 1-3)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1920s-1970 (0.3 linear feet; Box 2-3, OV 4)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1924-1961 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Grigory Gluckmann measure 2.4 linear feet and date from circa 1910-2003, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920-1973. The collection documents his career as a painter in Paris, France, and Los Angeles, California. Included are biographical materials, such as identification and immigration papers, awards, and exhibition lists; a few letters from friends, family, and art galleries; three notebooks; exhibition announcements, catalogs, and one poster; photographs of Gluckmann, his wife Anna, and artwork; drawings, prints, and other original artwork; and four scrapbooks containing news clippings and exhibition printed material.
Biographical/Historical note
Grigory Gluckmann (1898-1973) was a painter in Paris, France and Los Angeles, California.
Gluckmann was born in Vitebsk, Russia, and studied for three years at the Art Academy in Moscow. Because of the Revolution he left Russia for Berlin in 1920 and in 1924 moved to Paris. While in Berlin he changed his name from Glickman to Gluckmann. He had his first one man show in 1924 at the Galerie Druet and regularly exhibited his paintings throughout Europe. In 1937 he had his first one man show in the United States at the John Levy Galleries. After the occupation of Paris by the Germans he fled to Nice, France, and married Anna Sorochovitsch. They immigrated to New York in 1941 and moved to California in 1945. Gluckmann regularly exhibited his work at the Dalzell Hatfield Galleries in Los Angeles and Milch Galleries in New York. During his career he also illustrated several books. He became a fellow of the Royal Society of Arts in London in 1948 and the Benjamin Franklin Society in 1968 and continued to paint until his death in 1973.
Drawings; Painters -- California -- Los Angeles; Painters -- France -- Paris; Photographs; Prints; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Material, 1920-2003; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes biographical summaries and identification documents for Grigory Gluckmann and his wife Anna. Also found are transcriptions of reviews of his artwork; a few exhibition lists and exhibition records from a 1977 exhibition; two personal statements by Gluckmann regarding his artwork; and awards for his paintings and other career honors. Also found is a draft typescript and published copy of an essay regarding Gluckmann written by Arthur Millier for Dalzell Hatfield Galleries. Additionally there are records regarding Gluckmann’s memorial service including a copy of the eulogy by Otto Natzler and pages from the guestbook.
  - Anna Gluckmann Biographical Documents, circa 1970s; circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Honors, 1938-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Summaries, 1968-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of Cremation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Donations, 1965; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Lists, circa 1954-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Records, Charles and Emma Frye Free Public Art Museum, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - French Identification Documents, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grigory Gluckmann by Arthur Millier, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Immigration and Citizenship Records, 1941-1943; 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Service and Exhibition, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Statements Regarding Paintings, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reviews, 1931-1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified Russian Document, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Who's Who" Entries, 1950; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letters, 1941-1973; Series 2; 1 Folders Box 1
  The few letters found here include letters from friends and letters regarding the exhibition of Gluckmann’s paintings. Some letters are in French and one letter is in Russian.
  - Letters, 1941-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Notebooks, 1930-1971; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 1
  One notebook from the 1930s contains notes in French on concert recitals attended. Two notebooks, one in Russian and one in English, contain what appear to be artwork sales records and other lists.
  - Notebook, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notebook, circa 1930s-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notebook, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Printed Material, circa 1944-1977; Series 4; 4 Folders Box 1, OV 4
  Found here are catalogs and announcements for exhibitions of Gluckmann’s artwork as well as one exhibition poster.
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Annoucements, circa 1944-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Poster, 1954 (Box OV 4)
- Photographs, circa 1910-1973; Series 5; 1 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Photographs include portraits of Grigory Gluckmann, Gluckmann in his studio with models, and Gluckmann with his wife Anna. Also found are many photographs of Anna as a girl and young woman and one photograph album containing photographs of Anna on vacation and with friends and family before she was married to Grigory. Additionally there are miscellaneous personal photographs of family and friends, and photographs of Gluckmann’s memorial exhibition at the Dalzell Hatfield Galleries. There are also many photographs of artwork.
  - Portraits of Grigory Gluckmann, circa 1930s-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    Oversized material housed in Box 3.
  - Grigory Gluckmann with Models, 1929-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Anna Gluckmann, circa 1910-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28-32)
  - Grigory and Anna Gluckmann, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Memorial Exhibition Installation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, circa 1913-1960s (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1928-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Compositions, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Dancers, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Drawings and Watercolors, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Heads, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Nudes, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Portraits, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Salvatore Rosa Illustrations, circa 1926 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Womanhood, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Miscellaneous, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Artwork - Color Transparencies, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Slides, 1972; 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Oversized Portraits of Grigory Gluckmann, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 25-26.
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, undated (Box 3)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 36-37.
- Artwork, circa 1920s-1970; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2-3, OV 4
  This series consists of artwork by Grigory Gluckmann, including drawings in pencil or ink, a few painting studies, and prints. Also found is one sketchbook containing pencil sketches of figures, two printing plates, and an album of bookplates made by Gluckmann.
  - Drawings, circa 1920s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Book Plate Album, circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Painting, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Printing Plates, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Oversized Drawings, circa 1920s-1950s (Box 3)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 19.
  - Oversized Painting, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Oversized Paintings, undated (Box OV 4)
  - Oversized Prints, circa 1922-1923 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks, 1924-1961; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Found here are four scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements and invitations, and other printed material documenting Gluckmann’s career.
  - Scrapbook, 1924-1927 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook, 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook, 1934-1961 (Box 3)